Guide to the First Unitarian Congregational Society of Brooklyn records ARC.109
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 12: Scrapbooks., circa 1860s-1945; 2.25 Linear Feet In 3 manuscript boxes and 2 oversize flat boxes.
  The scrapbooks in this series are arranged alphabetically by topic and chronologically by earliest date within topic. Loose items that were falling out of scrapbooks were placed into folders which can be found alongside the scrapbook that the items came from.
  The books in the Scrapbooks series contain clippings and ephemeral items related to the Church. The scrapbooks collect articles on the church's ministers and on religious and ecumenical matters. They also collect some published images, poems, hymns, and local news items. Several of the scrapbooks include clippings related to Plymouth Church and Henry Ward Beecher. Most of the scrapbooks seem to have been made by members of the church. The scrapbooks of items on the ministers Alfred E. Goodnough, H. Price Collier, and Samuel A. Eliot and the scrapbooks collecting the sermons of Collier were assembled and donated to the church by Maud Willard Bartlett. One other scrapbook ("Religion and Theology, 1866-1875") included a note that it came from the home of Mary E. Butterick in 1942.
  - Ministers: A. E. Goodnough, 1887-1888 (Box 91, Folder 1)
  - Ministers: H. Price Collier, 1888-1892 (Box 91, Folder 2)
  - Ministers: H. Price Collier and Samuel A. Eliot, 1892-1893 (Box 91, Folder 3)
  - Ministers: H. Price Collier and Samuel A. Eliot, 1893-1896 (Box 91, Folder 4)
  - Ministers: Samuel A. Eliot, 1897-1917 (Box 91, Folder 5)
  - Ministers Sermons: H. Price Collier, 1888-1913 (Box 92, Item 1-2)
  - Miscellaneous Articles and Items, 1860s-1870s (Box 93, Item 1)
  - Miscellaneous Articles and Items, 1870s-1880s, 1937-1945 (Box 94, Item 1-2)
  - Religion and Theology Articles and Items, 1866-1875, 1880s-1900s (Box 95, Item 1-2)
- Series 13: Photographs., circa 1870s-1958; 0.25 Linear Feet In 1 manuscript box.
  The photographs are arranged according to their digital Object ID # in PastPerfect.
  The Photographs series contains photographs from two separate photo accessions related to the Church. Most of the folders in this series contain images that were originally part of the First Unitarian Congregational Society records. These photos were initially removed from the collection and entered into the library's image database under a V1989.20 accession number. The photos include church buildings, like Willow Place Chapel and the Third Unitarian Congregation's Unity Church, and church activities such as a picnic, fairs, plays, and some minstrel shows. Also included are photos of ministers from the First, Second, and Third Unitarian Congregations including John Lathrop, John White Chadwick, Alfred P. Putnam and Stephen H. Camp. The last folder in the series contains photos from a later accession, V1990.46, and consists of four print reproductions of photographs of Willow Place Chapel, Columbia House, and the school at the chapel.
  Item level description and digital versions of images from the collection are available for searching via the image database in the library.
  - John Lathrop, Parishioners, circa 1910-1958; V1989.20.2-.9 (Box 96, Folder 1)
  - Chapel and Church, Picnic, Parishioners, Reverend Hewlett, and John Manning, circa 1890s-1940s; V1989.20.10-.27 (Box 96, Folder 2)
  - Parishioners, Picnic, circa 1890s-1938; V1989.20.28-.32 (Box 96, Folder 3)
  - Ministers (Chadwick, Lathrop, Putnam, Camp), Unity Church, Unity Chapel, Unity Sunday School, circa 1870s-1930s; V1989.20.33-.41 (Box 96, Folder 4)
  - Windows, for Christian Register article, circa 1950; V1989.20.44-.57 (Box 96, Folder 5)
  - Willow Place Chapel and Willow Place Chapel Sewing School, circa 1890s; V1989.20.58-.61 (Box 96, Folder 6)
  - Columbia House Children, 1935; V1989.20.62 (Box 96, Folder 7)
  - Minstrel Shows, 1943, 1945; V1989.20.63-.67a,b (Box 96, Folder 8)
  - Christmas Mystery Play, Streets of Wonderland Pageant, 1913, 1921; V.1989.20.68-.71 (Box 96, Folder 9)
  - Columbia House Player's Club and Columbia House Summer Girl Minstrels, 1919; V1989.20.72-.73 (Box 96, Folder 10)
  - Lathrop Photo Album, circa 1890s-1910s; V1989.20.74 (Box 96, Folder 11)
  - Church of the Saviour interior illustration, circa 1919; V1989.20.80 (Box 96, Folder 12)
  - Bible Study Prints, circa 1920s; V1989.20.81 (Box 96, Folder 13)
  - Willow Place Chapel, Kindergarten, Columbia House Fair, circa 1900, 1917; V1990.46 (Box 96, Folder 14)
  - Christening Font, Unity Church, Third Unitarian Congregational, circa 1870-1900; Pearsall, Frank (Box Oversize Prints by Accession 11)
  - Angel of Light/Immortality mosaic by Louis C. Tiffany (Box Oversize Prints by Accession 11)
    Historical note
    The mosaic in this picture was originally designed in 1915 for the Unitarian Church of the Messiah in Manhattan. In 1919, that building suffered a fire and the mosaic was placed in storage. In 1935, it was purchased by First Unitarian. The mosaic had been commissioned by Julita A. Jones Parker to memorialize her husband James. She had Tiffany Studios install the mosaic in the First Unitarian Congregational Society sanctuary in Brooklyn Heights and it was rededicated as the Angel of Immortality.
    This black and white photograph depicts a church sanctuary which contains the Angel of Light mosaic by Louis C. Tiffany. It is not clear which church is pictured as it does not seem to be the mosaic's current home at the Unitarian Congregational Society sanctuary in Brooklyn Heights.
- Series 14: Second Unitarian Congregation., 1837-1967; 4.75 Linear Feet In 10 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically according to description.
  The Second Unitarian Congregation first split from the First Congregation in 1840 over dissatisfaction with Minister Fredrick Holland. The congregations united in 1842 (after Holland's resignation) but split again in 1851. The Second Unitarian Congregation series represents the records of the Second Unitarian Congregation during both of these splits.
  The Congregation's first permanent minister was Samuel Longfellow, installed in 1853. The Second Unitarian Congregation took a progressive stance under Longfellow who occasionally preached against slavery and delivered an infamous sermon in praise of John Brown. Some of Longfellow's sermons can be found in the file on him. A parishioner's complaint and resignation of his pew in reaction to Longfellow's John Brown sermon can be found in the "Finances: Pew Rentals" folder. Longfellow's tenure was followed by Nahor A. Staples who also included abolitionist views in his sermons. The Second Congregation's influential minister John White Chadwick (installed 1864) is also well represented in this series through his correspondence, sermons and articles written by and about him, particularly memorials after his death.
  The series contains records related to the regular functions and activities of the Second Congregation including trustee records, financial records of pew renters and subscribers, committee reports and record books kept by the Sunday School. The series also contains many records of the Second Congregation's Branch Alliance, a women's group that did charity work and eventually folded into the First Congregation's Samaritan Alliance when the Congregations reunited in 1924.
  - Address Book, circa 1860s-1890s (Box 97, Folder 1)
  - Anniversaries Book, 1876, 1884-1885 (Box 97, Folder 2)
  - Annual Meetings, 1900-1925 (Box 97, Folder 3)
  - Bequests, Gifts, and Memorials, 1896-1925 (Box 97, Folder 4)
  - Branch Alliance: Cash Book, 1887-1907 (Box 97, Folder 5)
  - Branch Alliance: History, Undated (Box 97, Folder 6)
  - Branch Alliance: Meeting Minutes, 1887-1896 (Box 97, Folder 7-8)
  - Branch Alliance: Meeting Minutes, 1896-1920 (Box 98, Folder 1-5)
  - Branch Alliance: Post Office Mission, 1888-1906 (Box 98, Folder 6)
  - Branch Alliance: Reports and Petitions to the Trustees, 1862-1921 (Box 98, Folder 7)
  - Branch Alliance: Reports of the Beneficence Committee, 1911-1917 (Box 99, Folder 1)
  - Buildings: Alterations and Repairs, 1867-1896 (Box 99, Folder 2)
  - Buildings: Building Fund Subscriber Signatures, 1857 (Box 99, Folder 3)
  - Buildings: Deeds, Leases, and Insurance, 1837-1921 (Box 99, Folder 4)
  - Buildings: Roofing Samples, 1918 (Box 99, Folder 5)
  - Buildings: Sale and Lease of Property to Syrian Protestant Church, 1925 (Box 99, Folder 6)
  - By-Laws, 1855-1908 (Box 99, Folder 7)
  - Calendars, 1914-1924 (Box 99, Folder 8)
  - Church Home Book (Membership), 1908-1923 (Box 99, Folder 9)
  - Committee Reports, 1842-1920 (Box 99, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1891-1919, 1925, 1943 (Box 99, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence: First Unitarian Congregation, 1913, 1921-1925 (Box 100, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence: Other Churches, 1853-1914 (Box 100, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence: Welfare Organizations, 1858-1897 (Box 100, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Bills and Operating Costs, 1877-1896 (Box 100, Folder 4)
  - Finances: Cash Book, 1858-1917 (Box 100, Folder 5-9)
  - Finances: Cash Book, 1918-1924 (Box 101, Folder 1)
  - Finances: General, 1857-1873 (Box 101, Folder 2)
  - Finances: Ledger of Accounts, 1903-1924 (Box 101, Folder 3)
  - Finances: Pew Rentals, 1850s-1873 (Box 101, Folder 4)
  - Finances: Pew Rentals Ledger, 1897-1904 (Box 102, Item 1)
  - Finances: Pew Rentals and Subscribers Ledger, 1911-1916 (Box 102, Item 2)
  - Finances: Subscribers Ledger, 1852-1859 (Box 102, Item 3)
  - Finances: Subscribers, 1851-1873 (Box 103, Folder 1)
  - Finances: Treasurer's Records, 1843-1873, 1917-1918 (Box 103, Folder 2)
  - Finances: Treasurer's Reports, 1851-1914 (Box 103, Folder 3-6)
  - History, circa 1900s-1920s (Box 103, Folder 7)
  - Incorporation, 1841 (Box 104, Folder 1)
  - In Memoriam, 1896-1950 (Box 104, Folder 2)
  - Mailing Lists, circa 1840s-1890s, 1917, 1925 (Box 104, Folder 3)
  - Ministers: Chadwick, John White, 1860s-1944 (Box 104, Folder 4-5)
  - Ministers: Dutton, Caleb Samuel, 1906-1907, 1913 (Box 104, Folder 6)
  - Ministers: Longfellow, Samuel, 1852-1905 (Box 104, Folder 7)
  - Ministers: Lyttle, Charles H., 1914-1925 (Box 104, Folder 8)
  - Ministers: Pulpit Supply, 1851-1853 (Box 104, Folder 9)
  - Ministers: Staples, Nahor A., 1861-1864 (Box 104, Folder 10)
  - Music, 1858-1896 (Box 104, Folder 11)
  - The Radical, articles by Samuel Longfellow and John White Chadwick, 1870 (Box 104, Folder 12)
  - Register, 1919 (Box 104, Folder 13)
  - Resolutions, 1910, 1918 (Box 104, Folder 14)
  - Sermons from other churches, 1900-1929 (Box 105, Folder 1)
  - Special Services, 1876-1924 (Box 105, Folder 2)
  - Society Meeting Minutes, 1840-1899 (Box 105, Folder 3-5)
  - Sunday School: Attendance Ledger, 1868-1882 (Box 105, Folder 6-7)
  - Sunday School: Attendance Ledger, 1893-1923 (Box 106, Folder 1)
  - Sunday School: Lessons and Exercises, 1873, 1880 (Box 106, Folder 2)
  - Sunday School: Library Ledger, 1866-1885 (Box 106, Folder 3-4)
  - Sunday School: Report, 1921 (Box 106, Folder 5)
  - Taxes, 1915 (Box 106, Folder 6)
  - Trustees: Chairman John F. Thompson, 1919-1967 (Box 106, Folder 7)
  - Trustees: Correspondence, 1854-1917 (Box 106, Folder 8)
  - Trustees: Elections, 1852-1909 (Box 107, Folder 1)
  - Trustees: Meetings and Reports, 1851-1865 (Box 107, Folder 2)
  - Trustees: Meetings Minutes Book, 1851-1926 (Box 107, Folder 3-5)
  - Trustees: Rents, 1853-1879 (Box 107, Folder 6)
  - Unity, articles featuring John White Chadwick, 1905-1911 (Box 107, Folder 7)
- Series 15: Third Unitarian Congregation., 1867-1958; 2.25 Linear Feet In 5 manuscript boxes.
  The Third Unitarian Congregation was established in 1867 in order to accommodate parishioners of the First Unitarian Congregation who had been travelling from the Fort Greene and Clinton Hill neighborhoods to attend services at the Church of the Saviour in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood. Frederick A. Farley assisted in duties as a minister until the Third Congregation installed Stephen H. Camp as minister in 1869. Camp became the Third Congregation's most prominent minister and in addition to encouraging organized charitable works and teaching within the Congregation's Sunday School he also shepherded the Congregation from their first space in Unity Chapel (built in 1868 with the assistance of the First Congregation) to Unity Church (built in 1886). The Third Congregation sold its church and united with the First Congregation in 1925.
  The Third Unitarian Congregation series contains the records of the Third Congregation's organization and operation including its by-laws, society and trustee minutes, resolutions, and financial records. The series also contains records of the Congregation's charitable work such as through the Branch Alliance, the Charitable Fund, the Ladies Benevolent and Social Society, and other clubs and groups organized by the Church. Correspondence regarding the merger of the Third Congregation's merger with the First Congregation can also be found here.
  - Accounts Book, 1871-1877 (Box 108, Folder 1)
  - Annual Meeting Minutes, 1889-1910, 1919-1931, 1936 (Box 108, Folder 2-3)
  - Bequests, 1927, 1934, 1939 (Box 108, Folder 4)
  - Branch Alliance, 1909-1935 (Box 108, Folder 5)
  - Branch Alliance: Accounts Books, 1897-1910, 1917-1934 (Box 108, Folder 6)
  - Branch Alliance: Meeting Minutes, 1897-1898, 1905-1906 (Box 108, Folder 7-8)
  - Branch Alliance: Meeting Minutes, 1911-1917 (Box 109, Folder 1)
  - Branch Alliance: Reports, 1920-1934 (Box 109, Folder 2)
  - Branch Alliance: Reports Book, 1920-1934 (Box 109, Folder 3)
  - Branch Alliance: Treasurer's Record Book, 1909-1918 (Box 109, Folder 4)
  - Branch Alliance and Friendly Aid Society: Accounts Book, 1919-1933 (Box 109, Folder 5)
  - Brooklyn Broadcasting Corp. (WBBC), 1934-1935 (Box 109, Folder 6)
  - By-Laws, 1905, 1924 (Box 109, Folder 7)
  - Charitable Fund, 1928, 1932 (Box 109, Folder 8)
  - Clubs, 1900-1903 (Box 109, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1897, 1926-1958 (Box 109, Folder 10)
  - Directory, 1925 (Box 109, Folder 11)
  - Entertainments, 1895, 1900-1903, 1935 (Box 109, Folder 12)
  - Guild of St. Christopher, 1890 (Box 109, Folder 13)
  - History, 1869-1890s, 1924 (Box 110, Folder 1)
  - Inventories, circa 1920s (Box 110, Folder 2)
  - Investments, 1928-1929 (Box 110, Folder 3)
  - [Lend?] a Hand Committee: Reports Book, 1890-1893 (Box 110, Folder 4)
  - Ladies Benevolent and Social Society: Accounts Book, 1873-1935 (Box 110, Folder 5)
  - Manuals, 1874, 1888 (Box 110, Folder 6)
  - Ministers, circa 1910s, 1925 (Box 110, Folder 7)
  - Ministers: Stephen H. Camp, 1869-1897, 1943 (Box 110, Folder 8)
  - Membership Book, 1922-1929 (Box 110, Folder 9)
  - Memorials, circa 1890s, 1926, 1935 (Box 110, Folder 10)
  - Memorials Books, circa 1910s (Box 110, Folder 11)
  - Merger with First Unitarian Congregation, 1935 (Box 110, Folder 12)
  - Mortgages, 1926-1931 (Box 110, Folder 13)
  - Parish Register, circa 1880s (Box 111, Folder 1)
  - Resolutions, 1924-1931 (Box 111, Folder 2)
  - Secretary's Book (Correspondence), 1897-1901 (Box 111, Folder 3)
  - Services, 1886-1917 (Box 111, Folder 4)
  - Sunday School, 1894, ,1899 (Box 111, Folder 5)
  - Society Meeting Minutes, 1867-1925 (Box 111, Folder 6-9)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1896, 1898, 1926-1929 (Box 112, Folder 1)
  - Trustee Meetings and Elections, 1918-1935 (Box 112, Folder 2)
  - Trustee's Meeting Minutes, 1894-1917 (Box 112, Folder 3-4)
  - Unity Church Building Deed, Insurance, Property Blueprint, 1872-1886, 1907, 1927-1928 (Box 112, Folder 5)
  - Unity Church Building Fund, 1868-1890 (Box 112, Folder 6)
  - Windows and Memorial Tablets, 1867, 1926-1927 (Box 112, Folder 7)
    Sketch of memorial tablet for Caroline R. Whitney
  - Oversize Flat Box 1 (Box OS 1, Folder -)